Guide to the Hendricks Family Papers, 1713-1976 (bulk 1755-1959) MS 295
New-York Historical Society
Hendricks Family papers
1713-1976
New-York Historical Society
Hendricks family
MS 295
16.52 Linear feet (31 boxes, 25 volumes)
The Papers consist of material relating to the Hendricks family, pioneers in the American copper industry and prominent members of the Sepharidc Jewish community in New York, and related families. They begin with the import trade of Uriah Hendricks (1737-1798) and his son Harmon (1771-1838), continuing with the manufacture of copper at the mill begun by Harmon at Belleville, New Jersey, and carried on by their descendants under the name Hendricks Brothers. They include business and family papers, including loose correspondence and business records, ledgers and account books, letterbooks, indentures, mortgages, deeds, maps, blueprints, journals, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, and ephemera. Among later additions to the collection, the correspondence of Henry Solomon Hendricks (1892-1959), president (parnas) of Congregation Shearith Israel, reveals the daily operations of the oldest synagogue in the United States for the period 1927-1951.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically unless otherwise noted in the individual series' notes. Oversized materials have been removed to two oversize (OS) boxes noted in the container lists below.
The Collection is arranged in nine series:
Missing Title
Series I. Uriah Hendricks Papers (1758-1828)
Series II. Harmon Hendricks Papers (1794-1863)
Series III. Hendricks Family and Partnership Businesses (1794-1928)
Series IV. Hendricks Property Records (1794-1911)
Series V. Hendricks and Related Families' Papers (1713-1966)
Series VI. Related Families' Business Records (1821-1869)
Series VII. Printed Material (1796-1875)
Series VIII. Manuscript Copper for America, by Maxwell Whiteman (1971)
Series IX. Hendricks and Related Families Supplement (1790-1976)
Historical Note
Chronology of the Hendricks Family Copper Business
1755 Uriah Hendricks arrives in New York City from London to start a mercantile trade in dry goods. The business soon expands to include metals and other materials for the carrying trade with the West Indies and the shipping trade with England.
1792 His 20-year old son, Harmon, completes his apprenticeship and begins working alongside Uriah.
1798 November Uriah Hendricks dies at 61 of yellow fever. Harmon takes over his father's business interests, discontinuing the West Indian trade to focus exclusively on the carrying trade with England and inland trade, particular in copper and other metals.
1803-1814 Because it is harder to obtain English copper during the Napoleonic Wars due to embargoes, duties, and travelling difficulties, the demand from American shipbuilders and craftsmen, prospering during the war, increases. Harmon becomes more interested in the manufacture of American copper, especially with the outbreak of the War of 1812. Works with Paul Revere, Robert Fulton, and other American merchants and manufacturers to find solutions for the shortage and produce quality copper.
1814 May Harmon buys the Soho Copper Works in Belleville, NJ, and invites his brother-in-law and former apprentice and agent, Solomon I. Isaacs to oversee mill operations as his partner. Renamed the Solomon I. Isaacs and Soho Copper Company, the mill begins operation in October.
1815-1824 Harmon recommences trade with England after the war. Soho mill becomes involved primarily in supplying the booming maritime industry, particularly steamboats, engineering companies, merchant vessels, and the Navy - as well as providing for the general consumer. Mill undergoes continuous improvements and expansion, bringing prosperity and employment to Belleville.
1826 Hendricks homestead (summer residence) built near Soho mill.
1827 Harmon's sons Uriah and Henry become full partners and mill name is shortened to Soho Copper Company.
1830 April Partnership among Harmon, his sons, and Isaacs is dissolved. Isaacs establishes new business as copper broker, Harmon retires, and Uriah, Henry, and another son Washington form new partnership: Hendricks & Brothers, with Uriah as senior partner. The reorganized firm finds new success in supplying the growing railroad industry, and adds mining, banking, and brokerage to their business interests.
1838 April Harmon Hendricks dies age 67.
1841 March Washington dies; brother Montague becomes partner.
1861 Spring Henry dies age 47; Uriah's son Joshua becomes partner. Hendricks & Brothers shortens its name to Hendricks Brothers. Wartime demands for copper keep business booming. Brother Edmund joins firm, becoming partner in January 1866.
1869 March Uriah Hendricks dies age 67; Montague retires from firm; Joshua becomes senior partner. Joshua's brothers Edmund and Harmon Washington become his partners and brother Francis joins firm, dissolving a partnership with Thomas Jefferson Tobias in Charleston.
1874 Soho mill renamed Belleville Copper Rolling Mills. Fire destroys much of the mill's machinery, structure, and many records. A new mill built within 8 weeks.
1882 Lull in copper manufacture and trade is relieved with Edison's invention of the lightbulb. Use of copper as a conductive metal provides a new market for Hendricks Brothers.
1884 Montague Hendricks, last member of the original firm of Hendricks & Brothers, dies.
1892 Joshua Hendricks dies; Edmund becomes senior partner. Brothers joined by nephews Edgar, Clifford, and Henry Harmon.
1895 Edgar Hendricks dies age 38. Clifford dies a few years later at 39.
1904 Henry Harmon Hendricks dies age 44.
1905 Edmund Hendricks dies age 45.
1912 Francis Hendricks dies. The remaining partner, Harmon W., retains sole control over the firm's interests. None of the bachelor's many nephews wish to join the family company.
1924 July Harmon W. transfers ownership of the Hendricks homestead at Belleville to the Park Commission of Essex County.
1928 March Harmon W. Hendricks dies age 82.
1938 December Instead of admitting outsiders to its leadership, the Belleville Copper Rolling Mills finally closes after 10 years of gradually reducing its operations.
Related Archival Materials in Other Collections
The American Jewish Historical Society includes collections of papers from the Hendricks and Tobias families also donated by Hendricks family members.
Related Materials at New-York Historical Society
The N-YHS Library holds one folder of Harmon and Henry Hendricks papers, 1824-1866 (AHMC - Hendricks, Harmon and Henry), and a letter book of Tobias I. Tobias, 1827-1839 (BV Tobias).
The Museum's collections include portraits of Mr. and Mrs. Harmon Hendricks, Mrs. Alfred Tobias, and Mrs. Tobias I. Tobias.
Scope and Contents
The Hendricks Family Papers consist of material relating to the Hendricks family, pioneers in the American copper industry and prominent members of the Sephardic Jewish community in New York. The material spans over 250 years, beginning with the import trade of Uriah Hendricks (1737-1798) and his son Harmon (1771-1838), continuing with the manufacture of copper at the mill begun by Harmon at Belleville, New Jersey, and carried on by their descendants under the name Hendricks Brothers. It contains both business and family papers, including loose correspondence and business records, ledgers and account books, letterbooks, indentures, mortgages, deeds, maps, blueprints, journals, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, and ephemera. Among later additions to the collection is the correspondence of Henry Solomon Hendricks (1892-1959), president (parnas) of Congregation Shearith Israel, which highlights the day-to-day operations of the oldest synagogue in the United States for the period 1927-1951. Henry Solomon Hendricks married a cousin, Rosalie Gomez Nathan (1894-1986), and through her the collection extends to papers of various interrelations, among them the Gomez, Hays, Levy, Seixas, Solis, and Nathan families.
Provenance
Acquired by donation from Rosalie Nathan Hendricks (Mrs. Henry S. Hendricks) in 1965, other Hendricks family members, Maxwell Whiteman, and by purchase. The supplemental material in Series IX was donated by Ruth (Hendricks) Schulson (daughter of Rosalie Nathan Hendricks), circa 2001. The bills of lading in Sub-series III.B, Box 12, Folder 4, are the gift of Peter A. Rabinowitz, in memory of Ruth Hendricks Schulson, daughter of Rosalie Nathan Hendricks, December 2019 (accession no. MS.2019.055).
Metal trade.; Deeds.; Diplomas; Diaries.; Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Ephemera.; Copper industry and trade; Mortgages.; Ledgers (account books); Account books.; Correspondence.; Certificates.; Stock certificates.; Scrapbooks.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Letter books.; Sephardim -- New York (State) -- New York.; Copper mining; Genealogies (histories); Congregation Shearith Israel (New York, N.Y.); Hendricks, Harmon,, 1771-1838; Hendricks, Uriah, 1731?-1798; Revere, Paul, 1735-1818; Hendricks & Brothers; Tobias, Charles, 1820-1855; Tobias, Henry, 1814-1846; Whiteman, Maxwell; Ophelia (Ship)
- Series I. Uriah Hendricks Papers (1758-1828), 1755-1798
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes material on the career and personal life of Uriah Hendricks, who established a successful import trade with England and the West Indies. His correspondence and business records reflect association with some of the leading English exporters of copper, lead, and spelter, including Pieschell and Brogden and John F. Freeman and Company. He also dealt with other prominent London merchants including the Oppenheim family, into which his sister had married. In the West Indies, his contacts included such notable merchants as Isaac Gabay, David P. Mendez, and the De Leon family. The series contains loose correspondence, inventories, indentures, letterbooks, ledgers, and account books, marriage contracts, and estate records.
  Biographical Note
  Uriah Hendricks (1737-1798) came to New York from London in 1755 to set up as a shopkeeper. His father, Aaron Hendricks, was a prominent London merchant with connections both in England and the colonies. Through his connections, and his own good business sense, Uriah was able to expand fairly quickly from a small-time dry goods shopkeeper to a successful merchant importer involved in the carrying trade with England and the West Indies. On the road to making his fortune, Uriah married Eve Esther Gomez, daughter of a second-generation colonial, in 1762. Together the couple had eleven children, eight of whom survived to adulthood. Uriah took an active role in the Jewish community in New York. He was a member and President of synagogue Shearith Israel and a regular contributor to charity and cemetery funds. A devoted father, he made certain his children learned Hebrew and received a proper Jewish education. He was a fixture in the economic life of the city as well, becoming one of the richest merchants in New York while still a young man. Wishing to maintain the safety of his family and his business, Uriah was not as active in the political life of the city or the country, but did profit by supplying the military during both the French and Indian War and the Revolutionary War.
  - Letterbook, 1758-1759 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and records, 1758-1782 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marriage contracts, 1763, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary fragment relating to estate of father, Aaron Hendricks, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1790-1798 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipt book, 1792-1831 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account book, 1795-1803 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letterbook 1797-1801 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Claims for release on estate 1798-1801 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter/invoice, 1791 November 24 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 1)
  - Ledger, 1797-1799 (Volume 1)
  - Ledger fragments and index, 1797-1813 (Volume 2)
- Series II. Harmon Hendricks Papers (1794-1863), 1797-1863
  The series contains papers of Harmon Hendricks relating to his importing business, trade in copper, and growing interest finding American sources of copper manufacture. It includes loose correspondence, inventories and other business records, letterbooks, ledgers and account books, indentures, and mortgages. It is arguably the most historically important of the collection and one of the richest pertaining to a New York merchant in the carrying trade who subsequently helped to build one of America's basic industries. Notable are Harmon's correspondence with Paul Revere & Son (Subseries II.C) and records regarding his ship, Ophelia.
  Harmon Hendricks (1771-1838), Uriah's only surviving son, began working in his father's business as an apprentice, becoming a partner in 1792 at age twenty. Harmon was especially interested in the metals trade in which Uriah had recently become involved. After Uriah's death six years later, Harmon took over completely, discontinuing the West Indian trade to focus exclusively on the carrying trade with England and trade in America, particularly in copper and other metals.
  Arrangement
  The business correspondence is ordered chronologically and then by person or subject. Some of the correspondence in Subseries B includes annotations and transcriptions as well as original materials. The personal papers, household expense records, and estate papers are ordered chronologically by subject.
  The series is organized into four subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Ledgers and letterbooks
  Subseries II.B. Correspondence
  Subseries II.C. Material on Paul Revere
  Subseries II.D. Estate-related papers
  - Subseries II.A. Ledgers and letterbooks
    - Letterbooks, 1794-1795 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Account book: 16 loose pages and A-Z index through Feb 28, A. Cohen, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ledger, 1795-1807 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ledger and index: estate of Uriah Hendricks, 1797-1800 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ledger, including some fragments, 1799-1804; 1813 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letterbook, 1802-1809 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ledger, 1803 November - December (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Two Blotters, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ledger, 1806-1808 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ledger and index, 1827-1830 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified ledger index, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper advertisements (2), Thomas Holmes invoices (3), United Insurance Company ship insurance policy, memorial and petition, records of copper and tin sale, petitions to government, 1799-1807 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 1)
    - Ledger book fragments, 1799 January - 1804 January (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 2)
    - Ledger: Uriah Hendricks estate, 1797-1800 (Volume 3)
    - Ledger, 1799-1832 (Volume 4)
    - Wastebook and ledger: copper transactions, 1800-1829 (Volume 5)
    - Ledger, 1803-1831 (Volume 6)
    - Cash accounts, 1808-1817 (Volume 7)
    - Letterbook, 1809-1827 (Volume 8)
    - Ledger, 1827-1830 (Volume 9)
  - Subseries II.B. Correspondence
    - Coen, Barnes, Oppenheim, Pesoa, and others, 1798 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Boldero-Freeman, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Freeman (invoices)- Levy, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Oppenheim-Pesoa, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Pieschell-Ward, 1799 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Berenberg-Freeman, 1800 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Gabay-Oppenheim, 1800 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pieschell-Ward, 1800 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bulmer-Isaacs, 1801 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Judah-Phelps, 1801 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Pieschell-Ward, 1801 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript list and typed transcripts, 1801-1809 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - DaCosta -Freeman, 1802 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Gabay-Henriques, 1802 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Holmes-Oppenheim, 1802 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Phelan-Sims, 1802 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Stafford-Ward, 1802 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Atkins-DeLeon, 1803 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Freeman-Hartford, 1803 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Hendricks-Holmes, 1803 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lansing-Phelan, 1803 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Pieschell-Ward, 1803 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Beck-DeLeon, 1804 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Freeman-Hendricks, 1804 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Holmes-Ship, 1804 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Atkins-Dick, 1805 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Freeman-George, 1805 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Harfords-Hendricks, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - McCauley-Ward, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Atkins-Freeman, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - George-Holmes, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Isaacs-Peck, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Pieschell-Ship, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Beck-Freeman, 1807 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - George-Hendricks, 1807 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - McCauley-Ward, 1807 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Ship Ophelia, 1806 August-December (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Ship Ophelia: disbursement ledgers, 1806-1808 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Ship Ophelia, 1807 January-February (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Ship Ophelia, 1807 March-May (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Ship Ophelia, 1807 June-December (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Suit against J. Franklin and Robinson & Co., notes held by N. Judah (1 of 2), 1807-1819 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Suit against J. Franklin and Robinson & Co., notes held by N. Judah (2 of 2), 1807-1819 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Freeman-Ward, 1808 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Freeman-Hendricks, 1809 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Isaacs-Ward, 1809 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1810-1816 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1817-1819 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1820 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1821 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1822-1823 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1824-1825 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1826-1828 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1829-1833, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Ship Ophelia manifest, seamen's agreements (2), duties on copper, United Insurance policy for ship Consolation, 1806-1831 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 3)
  - Subseries II.C. Material on Paul Revere
    - Correspondence, 1803-1805 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1806-1815 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Efforts by Henry S. Hendricks to authenticate documents, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II.D. Estate-related papers
    - Court decisions: property of mother Eve Gomez Hendricks, 1801-1802 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Family and household expenses, 1812-1838 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Administration, 1838-1844 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Expenses, 1838-1839 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Expenses, 1840-1842 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - In account with Hendricks Brothers, 1844-1846 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Brochures and maps of lots to be sold, 1846 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Deeds, maps, mortages, and other documents, 1846-1863 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Frances Hendricks release, catalog of alabaster urns, indentures, 1840s (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 4)
    - Maps, commercial notices of lots to be sold, 1830s-1840s (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 5)
- Series III. Hendricks Family and Partnership Business Records (1794-1928)
  The series includes records of businesses owned by the Hendricks family, wholly or in partnership.
  The series is arranged into three subseries
  Subseries III.A. Partnership with Solomon I. Isaacs in Soho Copper Company
  Subseries III.B. Hendricks Brothers
  Subseries III.C. Business and property of the Soho Copper Company and Belleville Copper Rolling Mill
  - Subseries III.A. Partnership with Solomon I. Isaacs in Soho Copper Company
    Scope and Content
    The subseries contains records of the partnership between Harmon Hendricks and Solomon I. Isaacs to manufacture copper at the Soho Copper Company. It consists of loose correspondence, inventories, indentures, contracts, ledgers and account books, and other records organized chronologically by subject, detailing the company's early attempts to succeed and establish clientele.
    - Articles of co-partnership and other legal agreements, 1814-1831 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Advertisement in NY Gazette and General Advertiser, 1815 February 13 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1815-1821 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1816-1837 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Partnership and other legal documents, 1813-1853 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 6)
    - Account book, 1827 April 1-1828 February 29 (Volume 10, Folder unknown container)
  - Subseries III.B. Hendricks Brothers
    - General correspondence and records, 1831-1842 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and records: Brainard-Harley, 1834-1850 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and business records: Merrick-Trotter, 1834-1850 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Bills of lading, 1836-1860 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Five bills of lading for goods (e.g., copper, coal, etc.) shipped to Hendricks & Brothers by the Steam Tow-Boat Company (April 5, 1836; May 17, 1837); Swiftsure Transportation Line (August 7, 1843); Lehigh Coal and Navigation Company (May 12, 1846); and Merchants' Despatch Line (May 30, 1860). Includes a photocopy or facsimile of a list, dated New York, September 7, 1816, of "Steam-Vessels, built in the City of New-York, under the Direction and Superintendence of Robert Fulton, or according to his Plan."
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Peter A. Rabinowitz, in memory of Ruth Hendricks Schulson, daughter of Rosalie Nathan Hendricks, December 2019 (accession no. MS.2019.055).
    - General correspondence and business records, 1840-1849 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1850-1859 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Pressbook of Uriah Hendricks, II, 1859-1869 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and business records, 1860-1869 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - General correspondence and records, 1870-1912 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Articles of co-partnership and related documents, 1893-1911 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Mill history, and newspaper clippings, 1908, 1922, 1928 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Stocks and bonds, miscellaneous 1879-1899 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Bonds: California-Maine, 1867-1892 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Bonds: Maryland-New Jersey, 1864-1891 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Bonds: New York, 1850-1903 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Bonds: North Carolina-West Virginia, 1882-1903 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Postcards and photographs of mill, Undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Hendricks homestead photographs, Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Brooklyn Navy Yard order form for tin and copper; NJ Oil vs Hendricks Brothers case, 1851, 1853 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 6)
    - Account book, 1831 April-1832 January (Volume 11)
    - Account payable and receivable, 1832-1835 (Volume 12)
    - Ledger, 1833-1835 (Volume 13)
    - "The Revenue Book", 1846 (Volume 14)
    - Letterbook of Joshua Hendricks, 1856-1886 (Volume 15)
  - Subseries III.C. Soho Copper Company and Belleville Copper Rolling Mill Business and Property Records
    The subseries contains deeds, mortgages, indentures, contracts, maps, blueprints, photographs, and other records from the Belleville mill and property and is organized chronologically by subject and form.
    - Deeds, mortgages, indentures 1794-1861 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Deeds, mortgages, indentures, 1876-1912 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Deeds and agreements: mining and cotton mill, 1807-1874 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Maps, blueprints, descriptions, 1809-1911 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Belleville homestead: deeds, maps, mortgages, 1820-1911 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Belleville Lead Company: deeds, maps, mortgages, and related documents, [1847-1862] (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Property appraisal, 1905 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Deeds, indentures, mortgages, mining agreements, 1794-1848 (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 7)
    - Deeds, maps, mortgages, blueprints, 1794-1890s (Box OS Small, Folder Y-Hendricks 8)